Today, we are exploring the breathtaking Channel Islands, little British gems just off the coast of France.
Now, I'm going to be staying here on Jersey and discovering the legacy left by world-renowned naturalist Gerald Durrell.
And I'm heading over to Guernsey to unearth the fascinating story of the tomato industry that once thrived there.
So I'll see you back here a bit later.
Now, Ellie is not the only one on her travels.
John will be setting sail to see what life is like on the tiny island of Sark.
I mean, it sounds to be a very old-fashioned kind of community.
Well, we're almost a step up from the Amish, except we've only got one husband!
Charlotte's back on the mainland doing a spot of weeding.
This is black-grass.
It doesn't look like much, does it?
But this resilient weed is rapidly becoming the scourge of British arable farms.
I'll be finding out why.
And Adam is meeting an unusual furry friend.
Now, we all know what a pig looks like, and we all know what a sheep looks like.
But have you ever seen one of these?
I'll be finding out all about them.
Clustering islands overflowing with exquisite coastlines, beautiful harbours and shaded lanes brimming with old-world charm.
85 miles off the south coast of England sits the largest of the Channel Islands, Jersey.
I'm on the north side of the island where one of our greatest naturalists spent much of his life - Gerald Durrell.
Appropriately enough, Gerald's first word was "zoo".
His dream to own one came true in 1958 at the age of 33.
He made it his life's mission to save rare animals.
Gerald Durrell died in 1995, but his extensive conservation work opened our eyes to man's impact on wildlife around the world.
But Durrell cared just as much for the animals on his doorstep and, later on, I'm going to be meeting a native of Jersey whose cry is being heard over the north cliffs for the first time in over 100 years.
For Durrell, self-sufficiency was hugely important, and it's still a significant philosophy of his wildlife park today.
I'm heading to a very special farm he set up here.
75% of the animals' food is grown on site, and I'm keen to see how they do it.
But first, I've got a job to do.
..Rubbish collection.
I'll just chuck these up on here.
I'm happy to help out, but I never thought I'd be emptying bins.
MATT CHUCKLES 'At Durrell Wildlife Park, nothing is wasted.
'Scrap office paper is the start of a recycling programme that 'saves around £6,000 a year.
'That's cash that can help more endangered animals.'
Well, this ash is a perfect example of Durrell's sustainable ethos.
The waste paper from the office was shredded and given to the bears to lie on and to poo on.
Their bedding was then dried, put into the boiler to heat the fruit bats, and now I'm delivering this ash to the farm so that it can go into the land and help produce food for all the other animals.
'Dan Craven is busy harvesting an unusual crop that you wouldn't 'expect to find growing on a more traditional farm, 'prickly pears.'
Dan, which of your wonderful creatures will be eating this, then?
The tortoises love this.
This is native to their environment.
We're going to harvest a bit of this now, aren't we?
Be very careful.
Some of these little thorns really mean it when they get into you.
Hence I've got the gloves!
You're more experienced.
No, I've just got thicker fingers!
OK.
So, what's the technique when you're trying to harvest dinner for a tortoise?
So, if we can take this pad, maybe this pad here as well, that'll be a good start for us.
I have to cut left-handed now I've got the right-handed glove on.
We're just going down at...
Yeah, cut just right down at the base...
And they're so sort of succulent.
That's why...
Oh, I've taken two off.
Two for one!
Let's look in the wheelbarrow and see what you've harvested.
Variety's the spice of life, they say, so we've got mizuna here, which is this sort of jaggedy leaf.
Sounds sort of jaggedy, the name mizuna.
We've got mibuna, komatsuna, and these are the kind of varieties we're not able to get locally, we have to grow ourselves.
And thinking back to when Durrell came here, he couldn't have chosen a better place.
He couldn't have, and it shows how far ahead of his time he was, because we're able to obviously reduce our transport costs, and this polytunnel is able to sort of produce the kind of greens that I don't think anywhere else is doing, you know?
And certainly not in the conservation world in Europe.
Well, you certainly know how to grow a cactus, I'll give you that!
Cheers!
Well, I've experienced some growing and harvesting in my time, but this is quite different.
Now, I'm down here, in an enclosure with the most endangered fruit bats in the world, it's feeding time, and, er, I feel like quite a target!
See what I mean?
'I'm hanging out with keeper Dominic Wormell 'and some Livingstone fruit bats.'
How often are you in here, Dom, shoving all this vegetation in?
They come in every day and they get this forage feed.
They don't want to hurt you, do they?
There's a real misconception.
Bats, they're the most wonderful things.
Look at these guys.
I mean, with their rounded ears, they're just cuddly, upside-down teddy bears.
Yeah.
And these are the farmers of the forest, you know, greater pollinators and seed dispersers than birds are.
When you're close up, like, they've got the most beautiful aura.
Yeah, they are just the most amazing animal.
Do you know, this year would have been Gerald Durrell's 90th birthday, and it just seems a real shame that he's no longer around to see all of this.
But from what I've experienced today on the farm and being so close to these animals, his legacy is still very much alive.
Now, one thing farmers on Jersey don't have to worry about is a stubborn weed called black-grass but, as Charlotte's been finding out, it's becoming a huge problem for farmers on the British mainland.
'This is Mother Nature fighting back.
'You could say it's the modern equivalent of one of the seven 'plagues of Egypt.
'I've never seen a problem like this before in farming.
'The whole management and even profitability of the farm 'is now controlled by this.'
This is a deceptively dull-looking plant.
It looks harmless, doesn't it?
But don't be fooled.
This is bringing arable businesses to their knees.
It's called black-grass, and it spreads like wildfire.
'Not that pulling at it will do any good.
'This field is riddled with the stuff.
'It won't be long before purple seed heads appear, 'giving the field the dark appearance that gives this weed its name.
'Black-grass IS native to the UK, but since the 1980s 'new, tougher varieties have spread across the country.
'Farmers try to control it using herbicides.'
The problem is, black-grass is increasingly resistant to those chemicals.
'This weed refuses to die, 'and farmers are running out of ways to fight it.
'Tom Bradshaw farms nearly 4,000 acres in Essex, all green and lush, 'except this field, burnt, bare and barren.'
What happened here?
What you can see in this field is a pretty tragic result of some of the pressures we're currently facing, so we've decided to spray this whole crop off.
But that's insane.
You've destroyed your crop, you've destroyed any hopes of a profit.
For this year, we have written off making any money out of this field.
We've got a big loss on it, because we've already spent money on it.
But when you look down into the bottom of the crop, you can see there's a lot of black-grass plants just in the bottom of the crop here.
Yeah.
And if we hadn't have taken the decision to spray it off, the seed return from those plants was probably going to mean we couldn't crop this field next year or the year after, and so it's a short-term pain for hopefully a long-term gain.
This is a huge field of nothing now.
No, and this was top-quality milling wheat we were hoping to produce here.
It was all going to go into the bread-wheat market, and we'd have probably produced about 160,000 loaves of bread from this one field.
That's bread which is not going to be on supermarket shelves any more.
'In effect, black-grass strangles wheat, 'choking it before it has a chance to grow.
'And because herbicides won't kill it, Tom had no choice 'but to sacrifice his crop.
'He's not the only one suffering.'
Herbicide-resistant black-grass has now been found on 16,000 farms in 34 counties, and it's spreading.
So how did it develop this clever resistance to chemicals which used to kill it?
'Well, one man who knows the answer is Dr Stephen Moss.
'He's come to take a look at the problem on Tom's farm.'
I understand you know a bit about black-grass.
Well, I've worked on it for over 40 years, so I like to think I've done more work on it than anyone else in the universe!
CHARLOTTE LAUGHS That may be a bit of a boast, but it's probably true.
So, you have some hi-tech equipment to help in the process(!)
What do you do with this?
Well, this is a quadrat, and one puts it over black-grass, and you go round the field at random to count the numbers of black-grass heads so you can get an idea of the density and then how much effect that will then have on yield.
I mean, this is a fairly high infestation, but you can get over 1,000 a square metre, and that's nothing like that here.
So, how come this has developed to be resistant, then, to the herbicides?
Well, black-grass is a very adaptable weed, so it's evolved resistance through selection, the rare individuals which have natural resistance.
And they build up, they shed seeds, and the population builds up over a period of years until you get perhaps a whole population that's resistant.
And actually, as we walk round this field, once you start seeing it, you can see it everywhere.
It's not the only thing, though, is it, that's resistant?
What other things do we need to worry about?
We have rye-grass, wild oats, which are resistant in the UK, we have poppies, chickweed and indeed mayweed, but black-grass is certainly the worst case, and it's the worst resistant weed in Western Europe, and it's one of the worst in the world.
'But there are those who believe farmers have brought 'this on themselves by being too dependent on pesticides.
'Stephen Fell is the chairman of Leaf, 'an organisation which promotes sustainable farming.
'He doesn't mince his words.'
I think we've forgotten how to farm properly, Charlotte.
We've got lazy.
We're growing continuous cereals, continuous combinable crops, and we've got away from good rotational practice, and we've relied too much on the fertiliser bag and the chemical can.
It seems a bit unfair to blame lazy farming, because that's with the benefit of hindsight, isn't it?
As far as farmers have been concerned, they're just doing the sensible thing.
Well, let's look back to the '80s and early '90s, when we had wonderful chemical technology and learnt how to use fertilisers, so our yields went up every year, we clapped ourselves on the back and said, "We're great at this," and then all of a sudden it came to a halt and the yields plateau'd and suddenly black-grass started to appear.
'Stephen claims intensive agriculture has overworked the soil, 'weakening its ability to nourish strong crops, 'and that's given the weeds a chance to take over.
'Farmers argue they've always used the best tools at their disposal 'and for a long time herbicides worked.
'However we got here, the industry faces a real challenge.'
Everyone agrees something must be done about black-grass, and fast.
So, what, exactly?
Well, I'll try and answer that question later.
'Guernsey, lying to the northeast of Jersey, 'just 24 square miles of patchwork fields and idyllic coastline.'
70 years ago this month, Guernsey was liberated from Nazi occupation.
For five long years, the island was held to ransom by the demands of its captors.
'We're all familiar with the stories of the devastation 'and tragedy of the Second World War, but the effect of the 'occupation on the farming community of Guernsey isn't as well known.
'The Guernsey tomato had been an important 'source of income on the island for nearly 100 years 'and an established part of the island's culture.
'In the 1930s, roughly 1 in 15 of the population were growers.'
But soon, this hard-working community found themselves on the front line of the Nazi invasion.
'Molly Bihet, who lived near the harbour of St Peter Port, 'witnessed the German invasion of the island.
'She was just nine years old.'
Before the raid, it was just a nice place to be, because there were so many...
People would meet there.
There was a lot of exporting, especially the tomatoes.
My grandfather used to go every day to have a chat.
It was a very busy place.
'The summer evening of the 28th of June 1940 was no exception.'
What were you doing on the day of the raid?
We'd been to a shop buying vegetables, and I had this...cucumber, and we heard these planes coming, and we thought they were British and we started waving.
Of course, they came down very low, and then all of a sudden we could see the German signs, we could see the machine-gunning, the planes came so low over the harbour.
Where did they fly from?
They came from the north.
We were terrified.
'Molly and her mum hid in a neighbour's cellar while her 'grandfather and uncle, who were at the harbour, hid under the jetty.
'But for the dozens of fruit growers queuing in the port, there was 'nowhere safe to run.'
What happened to the tomato farmers that were there?
The lorries were all burning, because they were full of tomatoes for exporting.
The drivers had got underneath the lorries, thinking they were protected from the machine-gunning.
Of course, they weren't.
'34 civilians died from the attack, and many more were injured.
'But the impact of the war on the island's horticultural 'industry had only just begun.'
'Suzanne Brewer is a third-generation tomato grower.
'Many of her relatives lived and worked through the occupation.'
How did life change for them when the occupation began?
Well, after the bombing down at the harbour, exports of tomatoes had to stop.
'The managers of the vineries had to sort of step aside 'and be told what to grow and when to grow it.
'Suzanne still has her family's diaries, 'which tell of the harsh reality of life at the time.'
It's incredible to have these.
Can we have a look at some of their entries to see what went on?
This is Uncle Arthur's diary from the beginning of the occupation.
"Tomatoes abound, and every cow and person is confronted with "the colossal task of eating 400,000 baskets of ripe fruit."
'But the surplus didn't last.
'By 1944, the islanders were starving and 'so too were the Nazi soldiers, who went to extreme lengths to survive.'
The tone in Uncle Arthur's diaries from 1940 to 1945 changes quite dramatically.
"March 31st 1944.
"I have had four robberies within 24 hours "and now they've been after my cow.
"No words of mine can describe the feeling of insecurity "about everything everywhere."
There was just an enormous amount of thieving going on, and sometimes it got quite violent.
There's another entry here.
Maybe, Ellie, you'd like to read it.
"Then Mr Mahy told me a greenhouse robber, a soldier, "had shot dead a German Gendarmerie man who caught him "robbing broccoli or potatoes last night."
So killing each other in their desperation.
'70 years on, and tomato farming under Nazi occupation is 'a memory held by a diminishing few.
'After a post-war boom, the industry fell into decline.'
In fact, there are now only a few commercial growers left on the island.
But there's a new project that's been set up with the aim of keeping that knowledge of the industry alive.
'One of the founders of the project is Jock Pettitt.'
What's this project all about?
Edible Guernsey is about bringing the infrastructure and expertise that was left over from the decline of the growing industries here and using them to teach people about food education and provide food security.
And starting with children?
Children getting involved is fantastic, because food education obviously starts young.
We've got people like Nigel as a mentor.
There's a few others who have significant expertise in growing on the island.
But we import most of our food, so we saw an opportunity to try and produce food locally.
'The tomato industry may be almost gone, but the knowledge gained by the 'growers of Guernsey in good times and bad will now hopefully live on.'
'Just a few miles east of Guernsey sits a place which has been 'described as "the jewel in the crown of the Channel Islands".
'It's not hard to see why 'when you take in Sark's beautiful coastline and patchwork of fields.
'But what's life like on this small island for the 600 or so 'people who call it home?'
You can't just fly in, unless you know somebody with a helicopter, because there's no landing strip.
You have to go by boat.
It's a 60-minute voyage from Guernsey, and this boat is carrying supplies for the island.
'Anything that's not grown or made on Sark has to be shipped in.
'It's tranquil here, 'because all motor vehicles apart from tractors are banned.'
How strange is this?
It's the first time I've ever walked along country lanes that have never seen a motorcar.
And I'm on my way to meet the Nightingales, dairy farmers who supply the whole island with pasteurised milk and cream.
'These Guernsey cows are the pride and joy of Chris Nightingale 'and his daughter Mary.
'Until he started the herd 30-odd years ago, 'all pasteurised milk was imported.'
Is there a different taste, do you think, to Sark milk?
Our biggest enemy at this time of year is the wild garlic.
Yeah, I've seen it everywhere!
Yes.
So you have to drive the cows like mad down the road so they don't eat that, cos if they get a mouthful of that it comes in the milk straight away.
So you've got garlic-flavoured milk.
Which of course is the last thing you want!
'There are no EU subsidies on Sark, and Chris rents his 50 acres of land 'on, would you believe, 'a year-by-year basis from seven different landlords.
'Farming is in his blood, but he's got far less security than many 'of his counterparts on the mainland.'
Everything you do as far as improving the land, re-seeding or anything like that, you're gambling that you're going to have it for another two or three years to get your money back.
What would you say was the biggest challenge facing farming here?
It's the sea.
If we were to import things, they would have to travel mainland to Guernsey, Guernsey to Sark, and the costs of those two stretches of water are very expensive.
And is there a future, then, do you think, for farming on this island?
Er, I worry about that, because it's good to have a balance of land use.
It's the way things are, and we're just fortunate that we've got seven landlords who are willing to give us the opportunity to farm on the island, you know?
So we're so proud now that there's no need for milk to be imported from Guernsey, the island's self-sufficient thanks to the loyalty of our customers.
'And I'm off to meet some of those customers now.
'This is a milk round with a difference.
'With no vans, I'm using a horse and cart.'
Julie, this is Sark's version of a taxi, is it?
Oh, yes, very posh!
It's either that, bicycle or walk, really.
And is there a strong sense of community here?
Oh, yeah, there is.
There's people doing things for people.
We're raising charity money all the time.
It sounds to be a very old-fashioned kind of community.
Well, we're almost a step up from the Amish, except we've only got one husband!
'First stop on my milk round is Helen Plummer, who runs a grocery store.'
I have your milk delivery.
Thank you very much indeed!
'Much of Helen's produce is local, 'from vegetables grown in the field opposite 'to shellfish and meat.'
It must be expensive, though, importing everything else.
Yes, it is.
You have to pay your shipping and you then have to pay your carter to come up the hill and deliver it to you.
I sense a great community spirit here.
If there's a wedding or anything joyous going on, we all celebrate and enjoy together.
But if anybody is ill or passes away, we mourn together.
And that is the way that the island goes.
'Life on this tiny island seems to be about everyone pulling together, 'but this close-knit community does welcome newcomers, 'people like my last customer, Caragh Couldridge.
'She moved here in 1989, and I'm delivering double cream 'to what the locals call her factory, Sark-style.'
Well, it's only a little factory, but I love what you make here, Caragh.
Chocolate!
Why chocolate on Sark?
When I first came to Sark, the first thing I noticed was how fantastic the cream was, and it seemed to me, "Why isn't somebody making fantastic "things with the cream?"
So, here we've made some hazelnut truffles.
The girls behind me, they do the rolling.
They come across here, and then we temper the chocolate in here.
What it does is it will set very quickly, so it doesn't give you too long to sprinkle on your hazelnuts.
I've got to sprinkle hazelnuts?
Sprinkle on the hazelnuts.
'Caragh started off selling her chocolates to visitors, but word 'quickly spread and now she has customers as far away as America.
'So, just how good are her chocolates made with Sark cream?'
Mm!
Oh, lovely.
Lovely!
I don't think I've ever been in a factory before which has such a fantastic view from its windows.
Well, I know!
We are very, very lucky.
We get fantastic views from here.
It is so special.
It's lovely to see the sea, and I think it keeps you sane.
'As I leave Sark, I'm reminded of just how much life on this 'beautiful island is dictated by the water all around it.'
Everything depends on the moods of the sea, and that creates an uncertainty that most of us just can't imagine.
But what really struck me was the strength of the island community.
They're all in it together, and it's that willingness to help each other that lies at the very heart of life on Sark.
'Earlier, we heard how a weed 'called black-grass is sweeping across arable 'land and keeps growing even after being blasted with pesticides.
'So, what else can we do to beat it?
'Black-grass, a real menace, 'especially when it invades valuable wheat fields like this one.'
If you don't get on top of it, then THIS will overtake THAT.
'As we've heard, black-grass is becoming 'increasingly resistant to chemical treatment.
'For many farmers, 'it's impossible to kill with products currently on the market.
'But we invented herbicides to kill weeds.'
So all this begs the question, why don't we just invent some more?
'That's a question for Jason Tatnell.
'He's herbicide technical manager for the chemical company Syngenta.'
We've got various research projects going on here, all screening different herbicides.
'I've come to their research and development facility in Berkshire.
'It's at the cutting edge of crop protection.'
Jason, what herbicides are farmers using which, actually, black-grass has already got the better of?
Well, I'd say broadly speaking there's about seven different classes of herbicides in use at the moment.
I think the sad news is that black-grass is now resistant to all of those to a greater or lesser extent.
All of them?
Yes, all of them.
We have been here before in the '70s, the '80s, the '90s.
If something became resistant to the chemical, then people like you just invented a new one.
OK, well, we are trying, but we need 100,000 compounds to find one potential herbicide lead, and then it's been taking up to ten years and £200 million to actually bring that to market.
So does that mean because it's too complicated and too expensive you're abandoning British farmers to be overrun by black-grass?
No, there's nobody here who would love to develop a new black-grass herbicide more than me, and we are looking.
The reality is, as I say, the process can take up to ten years.
'But Jason doesn't think it's a hopeless situation for farmers.
'In fact, you may be surprised to hear the following bit of advice 'from a chemical company.'
We would never advise the use of herbicides on their own, always as the pinnacle of a process involving other non-chemical means.
Herbicides are just one strategy a farmer can employ to control weeds.
The fact is, with black-grass we're in a situation now where no one element will win you the battle entirely.
Oh, come on, that's not what you've been saying.
Actually, in the past, you said, "Throw the chemicals at the problem, it will all be all right."
Well, rather like with the talk in the press about antibiotics recently, if you rely heavily and solely on one element, you are going to be selecting for resistance problems much quicker.
'Herbicide resistance means even chemical 'companies are promoting non-chemical methods.
'In fact, there's a growing consensus that we should be using more 'traditional solutions.'
Not entirely, though.
There is another highly controversial debate around the edges of this issue - GM.
'Glyphosate - among other things the main component of the weedkiller 'Roundup, is one chemical guaranteed to kill black-grass.
'Trouble is, it would also kill the wheat, 'unless you developed genetically modified glyphosate-resistant wheat.'
Now, some see this as the obvious answer to our black-grass woes.
Others, though, aren't so keen, partly because glyphosate is in itself a fairly controversial chemical and also because that would open the door to genetically modified crops.
'But farmers like Tom Bradshaw are looking for immediate solutions.
'Back on his farm in Essex, Tom's turning to technology 'to hunt down the black-grass.
'This drone uses special infrared cameras to identify 'patches of the weed.'
We hope that by flying over the top of the field we'll get a map of where the black-grass is out in the field, and then in the future we're hoping we might even just be able to spray out the target areas where the bad black-grass is and then re-drill another crop into that area so that we don't have the whole crop loss that we've seen elsewhere.
But killing off crops and starting again is a last resort.
As the weather turns against us, I've brought a visitor to Tom's farm.
Black grass expert Stephen Moss thinks turning back the clock is the best way to tackle the problem.
But that involves rearranging the whole farming calendar.
I think there is a need to return back to some of the old traditional methods of farming, even if drilling later in the autumn or spring cropping can help a lot because black-grass is very much associated with early autumn sowing.
For Tom that's easier said than done.
And it's not just moving his year around, Stephen also wants to see a return to more ploughing, which can bury the black-grass seeds and stop them growing.
And then there's fallowing.
What about the idea of actually leaving a field fallow, leaving it empty?
Now, that really is a last resort.
And I think that to convince us at the moment that we are going to be routinely fallowing part of the farm is a very extreme situation.
Tom, you're fourth generation on this farm.
How do you feel about going back to what your great-grandfather would be doing when he first got here?
Our forefathers probably weren't that wrong.
And maybe we've really got to go back to basics while using some of these modern techniques.
We've got to accept we need to change.
So there are some difficult choices ahead for farmers.
But there does seem to be a growing consensus within the farming industry, even between groups which don't normally agree that chemical solutions alone no longer work.
If we're going to beat black-grass and other superweeds, then maybe the farming industry needs to take a step backwards to move forwards.
On the north coast of Jersey, the scenery is windswept.
The terrain steep and jagged.
A rare bird, the charismatic red-billed chough, once made the steep cliffs above these shores its home.
But the call of the chough has been missing since the beginning of the last century.
Now a special team here at Durrell has been breeding this enigmatic bird so that its call can be heard once more over the cliffs on the north coast of Jersey.
She's very tame, she's very affectionate.
Sometimes she's not too keen on men.
Right.
If she doesn't like you she might peck you or jump on your head.
Just have a look at this mob here.
The keepers at Durrell use a technique called double clutching.
They remove eggs from the captive chough and hand-rear them.
The mother then lays a second clutch of eggs, potentially doubling the number of chicks.
She's absolutely beautiful, isn't she?
Lovely.
It's your favourite.
And I just hold my hand out like this?
Yeah.
I think she likes you.
When we tickle her like this, this is kind of acting like the male.
So preening her and kind of stimulating her, really, and that's important with foster rearing.
How far into this process is she?
I mean, has she sat on eggs and reared some?
Yeah.
Before we acquired her, when she was in Italy she had built a nest before.
When she came here she built the nest herself.
We gave her a dummy egg, which helps stimulate her to lay an egg, and she incubated it really well.
Once we'd artificially incubated an egg from another pair, we hand-reared it for the first five days to ensure it was strong enough to be put underneath her.
And pretty much straightaway she started feeding it herself.
She's really surprised all of us.
If I wanted to try and give her a little tickle, do you think she'd be up for it?
I think she might be.
Around her neck.
It might help if I start tickling her and then you carry on, it might work.
Good girl.
Darling.
Oh, she likes me.
Thank goodness.
It's incredible to be this close and tickling a chough on the back of the neck.
I never thought that would happen.
When Jiana's chick is old enough it will be released on the spectacular north coast of the island.
I'm heading to a project called Birds on the Edge, to catch a rare glimpse of these amazing creatures in the wild.
And I'm just in time for tea.
These are interesting looking feeding stations.
What's the story behind these?
Well, the idea is it's like a target.
It really is like a dartboard, almost, that the birds can see from the air.
They'll recognise it.
Shall we get them in?
Yeah.
Brace yourselves at home.
Turn your volume down.
Right.
Now, if we get back and they'll come in.
With the decline of farmland on these cliffs, choughs died out in Jersey during the last century.
Bracken took hold, stopping the birds finding insects in the grassland.
It's amazing how they react to that whistle.
Absolutely.
We started actually training them before they were released so they knew what it was.
Ideally what kind of numbers are you hoping to achieve?
We could get 200-300, maybe.
But 50-odd would be nice.
But this process, it's exactly what Durrell was about.
Absolutely.
Having an endangered species like this and managing it to restore it back into the wild and bringing the habitat back...
And working alongside the actual environment...
And it fits everything else as well, yes.
Eventually the choughs will be completely independent.
But for now, it's encouraging to see them making a return to the skies above Jersey.
Later on, I'm going to be finding out how these birds are getting a helping hand from some woolly friends.
Now, what happens if you cross one of these... with one of these?
Well, it's impossible, of course, but we think we've found the closest thing, so we sent Adam to meet them.
Now, you'd be forgiven for getting confused about what's in here.
The noise might give it away.
But with its woolly coat, it looks like a sheep dressed as a pig.
These pigs are Mangalitzas.
They come from Hungary, where the winters can be harsh.
They've adapted by growing thick, woolly coats to cope with the cold.
So in this farm in North Chailey in East Sussex, it must seem positively balmy to them.
And they're not only out in the fields, there's one in the farm cottage too.
Most of Phil Beal's pigs are raised outside, but this one was the runt of the litter and needed special care, so he's ended up as a house pig.
Welcome.
This must be Alfie.
Oh, my word.
The same name as my son.
Lovely.
I can see the confusion now - is it a sheep, is it a pig?
Well, now in the house, is it a dog?
He's definitely a pig and he's going to stay a pig, Adam.
What's he doing in here?
Basically, a litter of seven and he was fine for a couple of days but then started going off feeding.
And after about a week became quite listless and separated from the rest of his siblings.
So I pulled him out, brought him home, warmed him up a bit, gave him a bit of milk... ..and 24 hours later he was walking around the house as if it was his.
Is it a pig or is it a dog?
Exactly.
A dog looks up at you, a cat looks down at you and a pig looks you straight in the eye.
Alfie, come on.
Is he friends with the cat?
Yeah, they're very good friends.
No problem there at all.
Just makes himself at home?
Well, it kind of is his home.
Is she going to beat him up?
Eventually.
Look, she's had a go at him now.
Yeah, she will.
Going to retreat back into the house?
Yeah.
Off he goes.
What happens when he's a massive pig?
He'll be reintegrated over the next few weeks.
When his siblings get weaned from the mother, he'll go back.
Tell me about the wool, the hair on them.
They just produce this long, thick coat to keep warm.
Is it on their bodies all year round?
It can moult, just like any animal will moult.
Some will moult more than others.
If we have a hot spell it will thin right out.
Can you use it for anything?
I've heard of it being used in the past.
It's not something that's desirable, but it's possible to spin, and if it's possible to spin you can make something with it.
Let's go see the herd.
OK, let's go.
Alfie, come on.
Come on, then.
What happens with Alfie now?
Now we've been introducing him more with his siblings cos he has to spend more and more time with them because in a week or so his siblings are going to be weaned off the mother and he's got to go back in with them.
Yeah, bring a bit of food.
So the ones that have been reared on the sow are much bigger than him, aren't they?
Yeah, I mean, the size difference was apparent after three or four days.
But it's just started in the last couple of weeks, just to slowly catch up, so hopefully over the next month or so.
Just extraordinary looking pigs, aren't they?
With all the hair and wool over their ears.
Yeah, they're amazing animals.
They really are.
Incredible.
And various colours here.
Yeah, there's three main types.
There's the swallow-bellied, which is a darkish black-back With a lighter underbelly.
Then there's the red Mangalitza, which is pretty similar, but much redder than these ones here.
And then when you get to the east of Hungary, you get the blonde Mangalitza, which is what we have here.
How old is that sow?
That sow's now about three and a half years old.
They're a fair-sized pig when they're fully grown?
What have you got here?
We've got five ten-month-old Mangalitza girls here.
And what I'd like to do is get them through to the nice grassy paddock over there to finish them off for the last month.
Right, do you think they'll follow you?
Let's see.
They like a bit of apple.
The Mangalitza isn't known just for its woolly coat.
They're also famed for producing a meat with a high fat content, ideal for Phil's specialist range of salamis and cured hams.
With a commercial pig, you're looking at fattening them up to about five or six months old.
We take ours right up to a year at the moment.
And in the future we'll look to take them on longer than that, to get the best out of them.
Yeah, this for the last four, six weeks just to fatten them up.
They can graze away and really add to that great creamy fat that they produce.
Why do you want the fat cos most people wouldn't want too much fat on a pig, they want a lean pig?
Well, that's the unique thing about the Mangalitza and the product that we make with it.
And it's the air-drying process that the fat is really crucial to help it dry smoothly and slowly.
We're off to Phil's kitchen so I can get a good look at this prized meat.
It looks lovely.
The thing that strikes me first off is really the amount of fat on that meat.
It's quite deep, isn't it?
Yeah, I mean, you've probably got 20mm of fat there, and with the Mangalitza the fat is so creamy.
It's very high in monounsaturated fat.
And there's intense marbling of the fat throughout the meat and this really lends it to dry evenly.
How did you learn how to do the curing?
Well, we lived in Spain for ten years, up in the villages.
Come the autumn it's a ritual thing from each village to slaughter a pig.
At first I was just helping a neighbour, then it became a hobby, then it became a bit of a passion and now it's turned into a full-time job.
Wonderful.
I'm getting a crash course in curing hams.
No cooking required, just Phil's secret spices.
Then make sure that we're rubbing in.
Really rich.
Now we've got our cure rubbed in, they need to go in a bag.
They're going to be in the fridge for around three weeks, being turned every couple of days until the curing process is finished.
And then it will come out of the fridge and it will be rinsed off.
'And here's one fresh out of a fridge.
'And just like a haggis, you squeeze it into an ox's stomach lining.'
And then once you've got this all stringed up, it's into the dryer.
Exactly.
This is one of our drying rooms.
What's so special about the environment in this room?
We want this to dry slowly and evenly, not too quick.
We're controlling the humidity and slowly bringing it down slightly drier.
And the temperature, keeping it warm and just right.
And this will stay in here for how long?
This size will probably stay in here for about five months.
Goodness me.
So it is a slow process.
It's a slow process, but one that's definitely one waiting for.
See you in five months' time.
Of course, we've no need to wait that long.
Phil's got some laid out for us that's already cured.
Here's some of our range and then this is the finished product.
We're looking at something that's virtually 18 months in the making.
18 months to two years in the making.
Not something that you're going to put in your sandwiches every day, but a real treat.
Oh, yeah.
Good?
That is really creamy, isn't it?
Mm-hm.
Lovely.
I've got to say, Phil, that is some of the finest cured meat I've ever tasted.
It's delicious.
Obviously I have to quality test it.
It's not a bad life.
Mm.
(Can I have another bit?)
Of course you can.
We're exploring the Channel Islands and I've travelled from Guernsey back to Jersey.
Holiday makers have been flocking here for generations.
Drawn by the gentle countryside and stunning coastal views.
Once a Victorian hotel, Plemont became a holiday camp in the 1930s.
Since then thousands of tourists have passed through its gates.
But towards the end of the 1990s the attraction faded, the camp closed and was left abandoned.
Thousands of people on Jersey wanted the land reclaimed for what they believed to be its rightful owners - the flora and fauna of the island.
And what became a 14-year campaign got underway.
Mike Stentiford is a former president of the National Trust on Jersey.
He helped lead the fight.
I'm meeting him on Plemont's adjacent headland, Les Landes.
Tell me about the campaign for Plemont.
It all started in the year 2000.
This is when the holiday camp ceased to be a holiday camp and it was basically up for grabs.
And the developers moved in, started to put in a few applications.
One after the other, they were turned down.
The turning point came when more than 7,000 people turned up on Jersey's largest beach to show their support.
It was a huge, great passionate show of strength, that people really did feel very, very strongly about the coastline.
The islanders were successful.
£3.5 million was raised through donations and matched by the States of Jersey.
Plemont was saved from the housing developers and the site was demolished last September.
We need to keep these wonderful open spaces for body, for soul, for mind, for recreation, you name it, it is so, so special.
Well, you've certainly enticed me to go and take a look over there.
Now that the camp has gone, the real work is underway to get this site ready for its new residents.
And there's quite a lot still to do.
It's very barren, this.
It is.
It is at the moment.
It's changed a lot in the last six months.
Do you want to take a walk up there and have a look?
Yes.
Let's see how it was.
John Parkes is lands manager for the National Trust for Jersey.
It just looks so bizarre, like kind of a moonscape.
It does.
You can see why they placed it here, such a fabulous spot.
It may seem like we've landed on a barren, sandy planet, but there's a lot going on.
And in around 15 years this site will be as lush as its sister headland.
We've looked at Les Landes as a sort of inspiration of what we'd like to see here.
Dwarf shrub and heathland habitat is what we hope is going to establish here.
When the camp was demolished, many protected species including rare green lizards had to be saved and were placed in temporary sites nearby.
Oh, yeah.
Slowworm.
Protected species.
That's right.
And hopefully it will go and repopulate once everything's finished.
Hope so.
Is there anything I can do to help?
There's a lot of work going on today.
We're creating a few more ponds, so perhaps you can help us with one of those.
Yeah, I'll give it a go.
It seems like I've got a bit of help from some friendly firefighters.
Oh, I'd love to have a go at this.
Can I join in?
Absolutely, yeah.
Here we go.
Whoo.
That's got a force on it.
This is like a live animal.
And there's work to be done on the site's other pond too.
Here we go.
That's the last one.
Yeah!
Call that a tea break.
My work done, there's one last person I've been told I have to meet.
Nice to see you.
Hello, nice to see you as well.
'Stella Henley visited Plemont in 1949 when it was a holiday camp.'
What was it like?
It was a very basic holiday camp.
More like Hi-de-Hi!
You know, they said, "Good morning, campers", you know, like they did on the television.
You know, they had activities such as archery, and they had games.
There was dancing in the evening.
How does it feel to see the site like this?
It seems so strange.
Of course, I was all behind them returning it to nature, and what a wonderful place it'll be.
Then this place will become somebody else's holiday memories.
It will, and I'm sure they'll find a wealth of beauty.
It'll look lovely.
It's great that wildlife will come back.
We're exploring the Channel Islands.
Whilst Ellie has been discovering how the site of an old holiday park is being turned into a haven for nature, just around the coast, I'm also learning about a habitat being improved for wildlife.
The chough and other grassland birds once thrived here, but then the bracken took hold.
During the summertime, these hillsides are choked with the stuff.
It's like a blanket of bracken up here, so all of those species that rely on a grassland habitat to get their food simply cannot survive.
The bracken destroys the biodiversity that makes this habitat so special.
But the battle to banish the bracken has begun with the help of some Manx Loaghtan sheep, shipped over from their native home on the Isle of Man.
'This fine flock is looked after by Aaron and his sheepdog Mist.'
Why did you actually choose them as a breed to graze this area?
They're essentially the Land Rover of the sheep world.
They're a very old, traditional breed.
What that means is they're good on the grass, they'll manage the grass, but they'll also manage the scrub, they'll manage the gorse, and even, what we're really trying to achieve here, is managing that bracken.
How do they get rid of the bracken?
A lot of people think they eat them, but they don't eat the bracken at all.
What they do is they trample through the bracken backwards and forwards, using this mosaic of paths and networks that they use.
That kills off the bracken in the path, it allows the light to get in deep under the big bracken beds and starts to get grass and other broad-leaf things to grow where the bracken was.
And creates an area like where we're kneeling now, as opposed to just a big pile of bracken.
It's this fleece, really, that gives them their name as well...
Yeah, "Loaghtan" means "mouse brown" in the old Celtic term, so that's where the name Manx Loaghtan comes form.
So, in fact, we've got here a special little product...
Oh, look at that!
..Made from one of our fleeces, for you to give off to Ellie when you meet her later on.
I tell you what, it's an incredible...
It's a good likeness, isn't it?
Well, listen, thanks ever so much for showing off your fleece.
You're welcome.
You may now go back to all of your mates.
Skippity-do.
It's going to be a few years before the bracken is banished, but there are clear signs that life is returning to the clifftop grasslands.
Ellie, how are you doing, all right?
I'm good, you?
How does this view compare to the ones that you've seen since you've been here?
It's as good as the views I've seen.
It's amazing, right?
Yeah.
Have you noticed how the acrobatic sheep graze all the way down?
All the way down the cliff edges.
It's steep.
Very impressive.
Oh!
What's this?!
Woollen gifts from you.
This is becoming a habit, you know.
That's to go with the woollen jumper, the woollen hat and the woollen handbag that I gave you a few weeks ago.
Well, thank you very much.
Anyway, that's all we've got time for from Jersey.
Next week, we're going to be in Somerset where I'll be following in the footsteps of a legendary caver.
And I'll be testing my taste buds with the flavours of the sea.
Let's have one last look.